Guide to the Carol Schwartz papers, 1983-1988 MS2006
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Carol Schwartz papers
1983-2008
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Schwartz, Carol
MS2006
6.5 Linear Feet
The papers of Carol Schwartz relate to her term as a member of DC Council. The collection primarily contains documents relating to legislative proceedings that Schwartz was involved in as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia. These documents are contained in the series, Legislative History. This series includes a number of memoranda correspondence, notes, financial documents, reports, and official legislative documents. Some of the subjects addressed in this series include AIDS, Rent Control, and Tax Reform.
Restrictions on Access
Series 1 and 2 are closed to research for 25 years from date of record creation. Constituent files are closed to research.
Acquisition Information
Carol Schwartz donated this collection in 1993.
Historical or Biographical Note
Carol Schwartz (1944- ) has devoted many years of her life to serving the citizens of the District of Columbia both as an elected and appointment official including a considerable amount of work related to the education system in D.C. First elected to the Council of the District of Columbia in 1984, she served a four-year term from 1985 to 1988, during which she helped pass key legislation that had a lasting impact on the District. She ran again for the At-Large seat in 1996 and won elections to that position in 2000 and 2004. In 1986 and again in 1994, she ran unsuccessfully as the Republican Mayoral candidate in the District of Columbia.
Schwartz was born in Greenville, Mississippi and raised in Midland, Texas and later graduated from the University of Texas, where she received a Bachelor of Science degree in Special and Elementary Education. Schwartz was first elected to public office as a member of the District of Columbia Board of Education in 1974 and served two terms in office. She was then appointed by President Gerald Ford to the National Advisory Council on the Education of Disadvantaged Children in October of 1974. Ms. Schwartz was appointed as the Vice Chairperson of that council beginning in 1977 and continued serving in this capacity until 1979. Her political career continued as she became the Vice Chairperson of the District of Columbia Delegation to the 1980 Republican National Convention, and a member of the Presidential Transition Team for the Reagan Administration from 1980 to 1981. Schwartz also served as a consultant to the U.S. Department of Education, as a Press Secretary in the U.S. House of Representatives, and has participated in an exchange program with political leaders from various countries.
Schwartz's work with the Council of the District of Columbia has included the chairmanship of the Council's Committee on Public Works and the Environment in serving on the Council's Committee on Human Services, the Committee on Government Operations, and the Committee on Education, Libraries and Recreation. She has also served as Chair of the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments' (COG) Board of Directors in 2001 and as Chair of COG's Homeland Security Task Force. She was also elected Co-Chair of the Washington Area Housing Trust Fund in December of 2003, after serving as its Vice Chair.
Collection Scope and Content
The papers of Carol Schwartz relate to her term as a member of DC Council. The collection primarily contains documents relating to legislative proceedings that Schwartz was involved in as a member of the Council of the District of Columbia. These documents are contained in the series, Legislative History. This series includes a number of memoranda correspondence, notes, financial documents, reports, and official legislative documents. Some of the subjects addressed in this series include AIDS, Rent Control, and Tax Reform.
The second series Correspondence/Statements/Subject Files contains materials that do not relate to specific legislation, but relate to administrative issues and those of a more personal nature. These include correspondence, personal statements, and personnel files, as well as subject files on suicide prevention fences on bridges and South Africa. There seems to be gaps in some of the legislative proceedings. Materials within this collection date from 1983 to 1988, the bulk of the records date from 1985 to 1987.
Collection Organization
Organized into three series: Legislative History; Correspondence/Statements/Subject Files; and Chronological Files
Rent control; No-fault automobile insurance; Inheritance and transfer tax; AIDS (Disease); Washington (D.C.); City council members -- Washington (D.C.); Schwartz, Carol; District of Columbia. City Council
- Legislative history, 1983-1988; MS2006 Series 1; 1.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains legislative documents, correspondence, statements, memoranda, and notes and represent the history of Carol Schwartz's term in office from a legislative standpoint. The series is divided into nine sub-series based on subject content which are arranged in alphabetical order. They include materials on AIDS, alcoholic beverage control, auditor issues, budget issues, insurance, procurement practices, rent control, and taxes. Within each sub-series the folders are arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  The document relating to AIDS legislation include a history of the Whitman Walker Clinic Volunteer Program and AIDSwalk, as well as Ms. Schwartz's push to end insurance discrimination against people with the AIDS virus. Another major concern is the procurement practices of many District of Columbia governmental officials, in particular the Gutierrez investigation of 1985. Ms. Schwartz was also very interested in tax reform, especially in the cases of inheritance taxes and personal exemptions.
  - AIDS: The Black Community, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AIDS: Correspondence re: Insurance Discrimination, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AIDS: General Information and Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AIDS: Metropolitan Washington Committee on AIDS Issues (Bill 6-343), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AIDS: Prison Legislation- Problems in Correctional Facilities, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AIDS: "Prohibition of Discrimination in the Provision of Insurance Amendment Act of 1987" (Bill 7-364) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AIDS: Testing/Medical Legislation and Information, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AIDS: Whitman Walker Clinic Volunteer Program and AIDSwalk, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: "Alcoholic Beverage Control Act Reform Amendment Act of 1986" (Bill 6-504) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: "Alcoholic Beverage Control Act Reform Amendment Act of 1986," continued (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: Correspondence on Bill 6-504, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: Council Members Recommendations, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: Public Hearing, 29 September, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Alcoholic Beverage Control: Related Legislation and Notes, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Auditor: "Auditor Subpoena Power Act of 1987" (Bill 7-352) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Auditor: D.C. Auditor Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Budget: "Budget Accountability Amendment Act of 1985" (Bill 6-304) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Budget: "Budget Accountability Amendment Act of 1987" (Bill 7-66) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Insurance: "Compulsory/No-Fault Motor Vehicle Insurance Act of 1982 Amendment Act of 1985" (Bill 6-249) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Insurance: "Compulsory/No-Fault Motor Vehicle Insurance Act of 1982 Amendment Act of 1985" (Bill 6-249), continued (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Insurance: Sugar, Marvin L., Correspondence on Insurance Issues, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Procurement Practices: "D.C. Procurement Practices Act of 1984" (Bill 5-535) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Procurement Practices: "D.C. Procurement Practices Act of 1985" (Bill 6-191) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Procurement Practices: "D.C. Procurement Practices Act of 1985" (Bill 6-191), continued (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Procurement Practices: Food Procurement Investigation, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Procurement Practices: Gutierrez Investigation of Procurement Procedures, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Procurement Practices: Memorandums and Correspondence, Miscellaneous, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Procurement Practices: News Clippings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Procurement Practices: Proposed Procurement Legislation, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Procurement Practices: Proposed Procurement Legislation, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Rent Control: Correspondence, General, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rent Control: Miscellaneous Material, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rent Control: News Clippings, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rent Control: Related Legislation and Amendment Acts, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rent Control: "Rental Housing Act of 1985" (Bill 6-33) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Rent Control: "Rental Housing Act of 1985" (Bill 6-33), Council Members Recommendations (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Rent Control: "Rental Housing Act of 1985" (Bill 6-33), Referendum on Certain Provisions (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Taxes: "Inheritance and Estate Tax Revision Act of 1986" (Bill 6-372) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Taxes: Inheritance Tax-General Information and Notes, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Taxes: Inheritance Tax-Winter Legislation to Amend Laws, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Taxes: "Sales and Use Taxes Reduction Amendment Act of 1986" (Bill 6-432) (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Taxes: Tax Reduction Legislation-Personal Exemption (Bill 6-434), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Taxes: Tenant Associations-Tax Exemption Legislation, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Taxes: "Zero Bracket Amount Increase Amendment Act of 1986" (Bill 6-433) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Board of Elections and Ethics Legislation, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Child Stealing/Parental Kidnapping (Bill 6-274; 6-311), 1985 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "D.C. Enterprise Zone Study Commission Act of 1986" (Bill 6-431) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "D.C. Regional Interstate Banking Act of 1985 Amendment Act of 1985" (Bill 6-107) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - D.C. Residency Requirements Legislation, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Residency Requirements Legislation, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Eisenhower Southeast Freeway, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Taxicab Commission Legislation, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Urban Renewal Legislation, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, statements, subject files, 1985-1988; MS2006 Series 2; 0.5 Linear feet
  The series contains a number of statements, correspondence, and subject files that are not related to specific legislation. They represent general administrative matters or subjects of personal interest to Ms. Schwartz. Topics include materials relating to personnel appointments to various boards and commissions, South Africa, and Suicide Prevention on Bridges. Additional material consists of miscellaneous correspondence and statements of Carol Schwartz which deal with a number of administrative and personal concerns.
  - Appointments to Boards and Commissions, Requests and Resumes, 1985-1988 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, Schwartz, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, Schwartz, 1987-1988 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Office of Personnel-Confirmation of Theodore E. Thornton as Director, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - South Africa, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Statements, Schwartz, 1986-1988 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Suicide Prevention Fences on Bridges, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Chronological Files, 1999-2008; MS2006 Series 3
  General
  This portion of the collection is unprocessed. Some materials may be restricted. Please see Special Collections staff for assistance.
  (Acc. 2008.057)
  - Chronological Files, 1999 January; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chronological FilesPart 1, 1999 February; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 March; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 March; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 April; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 April; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 May; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 May; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 June; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 June; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 July; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 July; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 August; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 August; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 September; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 September; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 1999 October; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 1999 October; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1999 November; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1999 December; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 2000 January; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 2000 January; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 2000 February; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files Part 2, 2000 February; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files Part 1, 2000 March; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files Part III, 2000 March; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 1999 March 02-16; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 April 03-14; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 April 17-28; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 May 01-09; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 May 10-19; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 May 22-31; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 June 01-12; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 June 14-30; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 July 03-20; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 July 21-31; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 August 03-14; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 August 15-31; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 September 01-30; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 October 01-17; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 October 18-31; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 November 01-17; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 November 18-30; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2000 December 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 January 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 January 15-31; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 February 01-14; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 February 15-28; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 March 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 March 16-31; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 April 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 April 16-30; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 May 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 May 16-31; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 June 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 June 16-30; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 July 01-15; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 July 16-31; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 August 01-16; Series 3 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 August 17-31; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 September 01-15; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 September 16-30; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 October 01-16; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 October 17-31; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 November 01-15; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 November 16-30; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 December 01-15; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2001 December 16-31; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 January; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 February; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 March; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 April; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 May; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 June; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 July; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 August; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 September; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 October; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 November; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 2002 December; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 January; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 February; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 March; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 April; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 May; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 June; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 July; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 August; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 September; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 October; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 November; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2003 December; Series 3 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 January; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 February; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 March; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 April; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 May; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 June; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 July; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 August; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 September; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 October; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 November; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2004 December; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 January; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 February; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 March; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 April; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 May; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 June; Series 3 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 July; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 August; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 September; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 October; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 November; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2005 December; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 January; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 February; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 March; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 April; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 May; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 June; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 July; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 August; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 September; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 October; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 November; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 2006 December; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 January; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 February; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 March; Series 3 (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 April; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 May; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 June; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 July; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 September; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 October; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 November; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Chronological Files, 2007 December; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 January; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 February; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 March; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 April; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 May; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 June; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 July; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 15)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 August; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 September; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 17)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 October; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 18)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 November; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 19)
  - Chronological Files, 2008 December; Series 3 (Box 13, Folder 20)